Francesco Vurchio

Junior Software Engineer

07971 817 846 | francesco.vurchio82@gmail.com | Manchester (Willing to relocate)
<u>LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio</u>

Personal Statement

As a Junior Software Developer, I bring a unique perspective from my background in the fitness and health industry. My passion for problem-solving and commitment to achieving goals equip me with the resilience and adaptability necessary to excel in the fast-paced tech field. I am excited to leverage my diverse experiences to make a meaningful impact in software development.

Technical Skills

Languages: JavaScript, TypeScript

Testing: Test Driven Development (TDD), Jest, Supertest

Back-end: Node.js, SQL, PSQL, MongoDB, Express

Front-end: HTML, CSS, Tailwind CSS, Next.js, React, React Native, Native Wind, Expo

Hosting: Cloudflare, Render, Vercel, Supabase, Firebase, Netlify

Soft Skills: Paired programming, Technical Communication, SDL, Agile and SCRUM Methodologies

Projects

EventSphere | Event Platform to Share and Create Events | Solo Project | Repository Link | Website Link

- Developed a web app using React and Supabase for real-time database functionality and user authentication.
- Integrated Stripe for Payments, Google Maps and Google Calendar.
- Adopted an agile environment, emphasising iterative development and continuous feedback.
- Implemented features allowing users to view, register, pay or make a donation for an event.

Wax | Social Media Platform for Music Enthusiasts | Group Project | Repository Link

- Developed a mobile app using React Native with AWS and MongoDB for real-time database functionality and user authentication.
- Integrated Spotify API for fetching music information.
- Adopted an agile environment, emphasising iterative development and continuous feedback.
- Implemented features allowing users to explore, rate, and review songs and albums.

News API Application | Solo Project | Repository Link | Website Link

- Developed a robust API from scratch using Node.js, Express.js, and PostgreSQL.
- Employed TDD practices with Jest and Supertest to ensure functionality and reliability.
- Hosted with Render and utilising ElephantSQL for production.
- Deployed a UI news API application on Netlify, employing React for the frontend. Prioritised UI planning and architecture to mitigate development delays. Features user engagement with comments, voting, and content navigation.

Portfolio | Solo Project | Repository Link | Website Link

- Developed the app using React, Vite and TypeScript.
- Styled the app with TailwindCSS for a component-based design and productivity.
- Integrated Getform.io back-end to seamlessly utilise contact form.

Recipes Website - Solo Project | Repository Link | Website Link

- Developed the app with React, Next.js and TypeScript.
- Styled the app with TailwindCSS for a utility-first approach and responsive design.
- Integrated Formspree back-end service to communicate with the contact form.
- Deployed the site with Vercel for speed, performance and serverless functions.

Experience

Freelance Software Engineer Project Consultant | Tech Returners | July 2024 - Aug 2024

- Working as a consultant to deliver a bespoke web application for internal development, as part of the Launchpad project, including architecture design, implementation and deployment.
- Successfully integrated OAuth authentication (Google, Supabase) enhancing user experience and security.
- Backend Enhancements: Implemented robust backend solutions using Supabase, including user management, authentication, and database operations, ensuring efficient data handling and security compliance.
- Contributed to frontend development using React, improving UI/UX with responsive design and accessibility considerations.

Trainee Full-stack Developer | Northcoders | Oct 2023 - Jan 2024

- Completed an intensive bootcamp focused on building web applications, led by experienced instructors.
- Gained proficiency in programming fundamentals and test-driven development.
- Developed skills in back-end technologies including Node.js, APIs, databases, Express, and SQL.
- Enhanced front-end expertise in React and the creation of complex web applications and websites.

Personal Trainer | The Gym Group/Plant Powered PT | May 2018 - Sep 2023

- Established and managed a self-employed personal training business.
- Delivered personal training sessions, developed business strategies, and conducted marketing and promotions.

Senior Hair Stylist/AGM | Nino Milano Studio | Apr 2001 - Feb 2023

- Continued family tradition in hairdressing as a senior stylist.
- Managed POS systems, website, social media, advertising, and recruitment.

Education

BSc Hons Sport, Fitness & Coaching | The Open University | Oct 2015 - May 2021

Upper second class (2:1)

- Studied sports coaching principles, management, sports psychology, coaching methodology, advanced nutrition, and strength & conditioning.
- Gained practical experience in preparing athletes for competition.

Strength & Conditioning Coach | Strength & Conditioning Education | Jun 2021 - Aug 2022

Level 4 Strength & Conditioning Coaching Qualification

Personal Trainer | Active | Q | Feb 2018 - Mar 2018

Level 3 Diploma in Fitness Instructing and Personal Training

Interests

- Participating in cycling and running competitions, including charity events.
- Supporting youth involvement in climbing activities for physical and mental wellbeing.
- Developing a cooking/recipes web page to promote wellness and a cruelty-free lifestyle.
- Engaging in weightlifting, walking and yoga daily.